A professional digital detective
has dredged up
my publicly available information,
but what about the online information
that we assume is secure,
like financial details,
credit card numbers,
health records,
business correspondence?
When a business falls victim
to a sensitive data breach,
the consequences
can be particularly devastating.
In order to get a better idea of this
threat, I'm going to face it head-on.
I'm going to get
my Guardian computer hacked.
The first hacker struck
at a live telegraph event in 1903.
John Fleming was not pleased
that prankster and magician
Nevil Maskelyne
chose to insert insulting Morse code
into his fancy demo.
Modern-day hacking
started with a phone line.
Freakers, as they were known,
spent the 1970s making
free international phone calls.
In 1981, however, the first freaker
was convicted in the US for hacking,
but this hack helped to expose
the holes in the phone system.
In 1988 the Morris worm
hit an early version of the internet,
exposing vulnerabilities
in this technology.
In 2000 the Love Letter worm
infected 10% of the world's
internet-connected computers,
causing almost $9 billion
in damages worldwide.
It was a casually created joke
by two friends in the Philippines.
In recent years the new breed
of geeks are being hired
by governments,
financial systems and corporations
to both attack and defend.
I'm travelling to Las Vegas.
Here, annually, for the past 20 years
international hackers gather
to show off their skills
and exchange techniques.
We already know what can be learned
about me through a legal search,
but what can be uncovered
with specialist skills?
With my company computer
I'm visiting two hackers,
Khalil from Beirut
and Marton from Kentucky.
Can they hack my laptop?
What is the security situation
like in the Middle East,
say, compared with Europe or the US?
I think the whole region is somewhere
between 5 to 10 years behind,
as far as awareness of the importance
of information security.
Mainly because the media
doesn't really talk about it.
In the States,
you turn on any TV channel
and there's a story about a big hack
because these things are publicised.
Yes, I've just got an email
from my director.
He says there's a good article
on the front-page of the Guardian.
Oh, Lord, there's nothing
but bad news down here, is there?
- That's the world for you.
- It is, isn't it?
Except there's a cool picture
from NASA.
As you're browsing
through the Guardian,
I just stole your credentials,
so I have your email address... .com
and the password is...
- A nice Guns N' Roses song.
- Thank you very much!
I'm actually compromising
your whole machine.
I could have downloaded files.
I could do a rickroll,
which is redirecting your browser.
- Never Gonna Give You Up.
- I just sent you to Rick Astley.
You did.
How did you crack my computer?
The website is not the Guardian.
It looks like the Guardian.
If you look at it carefully, which
people don't really do, on the URL,
it actually says "theguardlian",
so I added an "L" in there.
- But...
- Yes, you did. You did?
- Yes, I...
- It was added?
I registered the website,
the guardlian.com.
- That's available?
- It was. Not any more.
And so I cloned a live version
of the actual Guardian website,
so you wouldn't know
you're not there.
No, it looks exactly
like the Guardian.
It's enough to take control
of your whole computer
because you gave me access,
just clicking on the link.
I clicked through to the link
from a person
who sent me an email whom I trust.
Your Facebook and your LinkedIn
is out there.
We can find out
who you're associated with.
Then we can get their email
out of their LinkedIn or Facebook.
It's a very easy fake.
Is it as easy to do this
to company computers?
It's probably easier
because out of 100 or 1,000 people,
it's more probable
some of them will click the link.
Every year, international hackers
converge in Las Vegas
to attend a series of conferences -
Def Con, BSides and Black Hat.
Over a few weeks they exchange
the latest hacking
and security tricks and techniques.
We're here in Vegas,
kind of in the belly of the beast.
Are there any examples
of this kind of exploitation
happening in the wild?
Sure, in the old days,
and I mean five years ago,
we used to do
a lot of USB-based attacks
where we would drop them
around parking lots
and that was really common.
So what I want you to do
is plug that in.
For one, you don't ever want
to stick anything into your computer
that you don't actually know
what it is.
At this point I can do anything
I want to your computer.
I can do a key logger.
I can download and upload files.
You can see here that we're here
in the C:/Users/Aleksdirectory.
We noticed you have some business
files and some personal files.
- I do, yes.
- We'll download to our computer.
I don't want you to have that.
Now we can do a lot of things.
I could take screen shots
from your camera.
- Of me?
- Of you.
We can record the sound.
And then we're able
to download a file to your computer.
It's moving.
And set it
to your desktop background.
That's a fantastic picture, guys.
- I've been hacked.
- Correct.
What about for corporations?
How are they vulnerable with this?
We've done
a number of penetration tests
where we've gone
to our local computer store.
We've bought 10 or 20 keyboards
and slotted one of these devices in
and packed them up
and sent them to the company.
What we've done is
put a fake letter in there that says,
"Hey, we're from HP. We want you
to check out our new keyboard.
"We're hoping if we give you
these 20 free models
"you'll buy 10,000 of them
because they're so great.
"Try these out."
Nobody resists free stuff.
If you make it expensive enough
and nice enough, people will use it.
But humans are humans.
Is there anything companies can do?
It's awareness training.
You can have
all the firewalls you want
and all the password policies.
If they get online and click on any
link, then it renders all that moot.
Sometimes we have to sacrifice
some convenience for safety.
If it's too good to be true,
either in an email format
or something you found
or something somebody sent you,
it probably is.
Wow! It was quite unsettling
to see how easy it was to get hacked.
But the consequences of getting
hacked aren't always destructive.
Sometimes it ends up exposing
corporate vulnerabilities or flaws
that a business can address
and improve upon.
From this hack, the Guardian will be
more astute with domain registration.
In the next episode,
I'll explore how to take control
when you lose control
of your online image
and negative information
about you or your business
ends up splashed
all over the web.