Often companies and individuals
who are in the public eye
are targeted on the Internet.
Throughout the 2000s
I was a fixture on UK television.
Thankfully I haven't fallen victim
to my personal or professional data
being hacked or leaked,
but what if I had?
I'm going to meet three experts
who specialise in taking control back
when the worst happens.
I'm travelling to Romania
to speak with Mario Gonzales.
He was in a legal battle for a decade
with Google, and in the end,
he was successful in his quest
to remove a document from their index
that compromised his reputation.
In doing so, he helped to herald
in a new statutory right
that's been exercised
by over 200,000 European citizens -
the right to be forgotten.
Why was getting your data
removed from the search engine
such a significant battle for you?
It was important
as a matter of principle.
I thought, "Why should
my personal data be out there?
"I don't want it to be."
This new law allows us to remove data
that is incorrect or harmful
to individuals from search engines.
One of the problems with your case
is because you took Google to court
to get rid of the information
that information is the first thing
that comes up on your Wikipedia page.
It's a paradox.
Yes, it's a paradox.
At this moment
it is practically impossible
to completely remove something
from the Internet.
But the multiplying effect
of a search engine is very important.
I'm meeting with Alastair,
who works with businesses
advising them on managing their
online reputations in Data Shadows.
Will the situation for companies
be similar
when they find undesirable material
has been leaked online?
When you've published something
online, you've lost control of it.
Be conscious that if you put
something on the Internet,
there's no guarantee that it stays
secure and under your control.
Companies need to have
some sort of incident-handling plan
to know when something does occur,
and it will,
how they are going to respond to that
so it isn't a panic in the business.
Many companies have moved
to adopt the new technologies
because they bring business benefit,
but they've not thought about the risks.
How do you ensure that information
doesn't make you vulnerable?
It really depends where the data is,
so if it's linked through somewhere
like Google, Twitter, Facebook,
there are removable procedures
you can go through.
But if your data is
on a Russian hacker site somewhere,
they're unlikely to respond
to a take-down request.
The best you can do is try
to mitigate the consequences.
So, for businesses and individuals,
once the information is out,
it seems nearly impossible
to take back control of it.
Since the earliest days
of human communication,
we quickly learn the importance
of confidentiality.
It's been good business.
3,000 years ago in the Middle East
potters used cryptography
to keep their glaze formula
secret from competitors.
Particularly during conflict.
Protecting correspondence has
always been of the utmost importance.
But it wasn't just military and business
information we sought to protect.
In 400 BC
the writers of the Kama Sutra
recommended that lovers
encrypt their messages
to keep them from prying eyes.
Now in the 21st century
we're exchanging more business
and personal information
than ever before,
though we've relinquished control
of this data
to governments and corporations.
Often instead of safekeeping
this material,
we've found
that they're exploiting it.
To learn about preventative
techniques I'm travelling to Berlin
to meet with Stephanie Hankey
from Tactical Technology.
Their organisation works
to provide tips, tools and techniques
for individuals,
like journalists and activists
whose lives depend upon retaining
control of their digital activities.
If you're interviewing people,
it may be as important
that somebody from the outside
can't see who you're talking to.
A phone call that we might have,
we might think it needs to be encrypted,
so people don't know
what we're talking about.
Very often what's more important
is that we're having a conversation,
but also we talked last week
and that today we talked for an hour.
That's metadata.
What other forms of data
might be collected about me?
In a city, for the phone to know
where you are, to look at a map,
you have to have location data on.
If you look on your iPhone,
in the System Services section...
Lo and behold, down,
somewhere buried in the menu.
There's a "frequent locations".
Most people are surprised.
It gives an overview of something.
It guesses what your home is.
When you start
to look at the patterns,
you see things like probably when
you come into the house after work,
when you leave in the morning.
What you can do
is switch off Location Services.
So what are companies
doing with this metadata?
These companies
are not yet transparent about it.
Some is profiling and advertising.
Some of it has gone much further.
For example, LinkedIn is using their
large-scale analysis of the data
to advise governments
and that becomes complicated.
People are not thinking
they're contributing to that.
Personal data
is the oil of the 21st century.
All technological companies
are gathering and using data
as they know it is now essential
to their business.
But what happens if this data
was accessible for us all to use,
rather than just a handful
of companies?
In the next episode, I'll dive
into open data to show the power
of digital collaboration.