In the modern world, a huge amount
of information is collected about us
as we go about our daily lives.
Whether we disclose it
willingly or unwittingly,
this valuable data is now a commodity
that is traded
amongst a handful of companies.
But what if there was a way to
harness it for the collective good?
In this episode I'll use my data
to help map the fallout
of the Fukushima nuclear disaster.
Trading data is hardly a new thing.
We've always benefitted
from sharing information.
It's helped to advance civilisation.
The internet is the latest
in a long line of technologies
that have ushered in
great innovations and social change.
Trade routes introduced mathematics
and astronomy from Arabia,
weapons and vaccinations from China
and spices and philosophies
from the subcontinent.
The printing press
blew apart traditional hierarchies,
letting the people
interpret and proclaim,
rather than those in power.
The telegraph
brought the world closer together,
disrupting business,
governance and the judicial system.
And every step of the way the powers
that be tried to claw back control.
Today there are three-billion people
communicating through the internet.
This latest network has given
each of us the empowering ability
to collaborate, share and exchange
information rapidly and efficiently.
I'm headed to Japan where I'm going
to volunteer to test radiation levels
using a community-built
Geiger counter.
After the disaster in March 2011,
information about radiation hazards
that was being released
by the government
was at best incomplete,
often contradictory
and ultimately not really reliable.
So we felt it was one thing to say,
"My government tells me radiation
level is X. I guess I'll believe it."
Or to go and measure it yourself.
If you measure it yourself, you can
have confidence in that data.
SafeCast was really formed
to allow citizens
to gather the information they needed
and to disseminate it in a free way.
SafeCast Geiger kits are open-source.
Through building the devices,
people learn how the technology works
and as a consequence
many have offered
both hardware
and software improvements.
This has helped
to rapidly evolve the design.
In 18 months SafeCast
went from a very large bulky system
with a detector
on the outside of the car
that required
being tethered to a laptop
down to this very small nano,
which is the current unit.
Seven separate designs in 18 months.
We think it's more than any startup
in any universe has ever done.
If I were a company
or an institution,
how long would it take me to do one?
Sometimes two years
for a new product.
Nobody does it so quickly.
The only reason
we're able to do it
is because we leverage these
open-source tools to speed this up.
You opened it up and said "This is
what we're thinking about doing"
The community came back and said
you could do it... better this way?
It's a bit chaotic in ways, but
it's very quick, agile and flexible.
People from all sorts of walks
of life participate -
anti-nuclear or pro-nuclear.
Teachers, housewives -
anyone can build it and submit data.
How can organisations wisely protect
the data that they're collecting?
The most important thing we found
the need to protect is privacy.
The privacy of volunteers. We allow
them to participate anonymously.
In Fukushima Prefecture
there was concern that people
would have radiation levels
in their front yard publicised
and that this could
affect them negatively.
Because of that, we decided
to use a hardware hack
to allow them to put the data
in a grid of 100 metres
that doesn't identify that data spot
with a particular person's property.
How much of Japan has been mapped?
We argue that we have been able
to provide a wider coverage
of radiation surveys
than the government has
because of the activities
of very active volunteers.
Certainly, Fukushima
has been repeatedly mapped
for three years or more.
There are a few corners
no volunteers have been to,
so today we can go
to a park in Koto Ward,
called Kiyosumi Park,
and we can check that out.
We're looking
at 0.1 microsieverts per hour.
This is about normal.
Pretty average for Tokyo.
How does that compare with,
say, the epicentre of the accident?
This is a piece of a deck that
one of our volunteers was building
when the disaster happened
in Koriyama,
which is one of the fairly
radioactive places in Fukushima.
- Listen to that!
- Yes.
You can hear it.
It's like a scary noise.
It's already now 10 times
what it was...
- This is a very radioactive sample.
- That is significantly higher.
And this is the degree of fallout
that was everywhere in that area.
Inside the highly radioactive places
in Fukushima Daiichi reactor itself,
it's 1,000 times higher, or more.
We're getting to a point
where technically, because
of the hardware and software tools,
things that were
previously only possible
if you were a government
or a large research institution,
now a highschool kid can do.
This is going to get better,
quicker, easier and cheaper.
We are trying to show that potential.
This is an example of the agile
development organisations can use
when they open up
and engage their contributors.
By introducing privacy measures,
SafeCast has built confidence
in their project
and trust amongst
their collaborators.
This is an increasingly
important consideration,
as by 2020 it's estimated
that there will be 30-billion things
connected to the internet,
from transport, medical devices,
to household objects,
all of which will be collecting
and transmitting our information.
In the next episode, I'll explore
the privacy and data implications
by spending 24 hours
in a technology-laden smarthome.